Benjamin Houghton: Alright, so…
Benjamin Houghton: This says introduction to Vision Transformers. Think a bit more about, like, the fundamentals that you're going to need to know for the rest of the semester and other topics. Like I said, these things will come up, like, repeatedly, probably throughout the rest of the year, and this is kind of just, like, your first
Benjamin Houghton: high-level overview to them. So, as we know, CNNs have been… have been pretty dominant in vision tasks, and
Benjamin Houghton: They have a very, very strong spatial inductive biases, which means that they have this translational equivariance and locality, right? Meaning that, what does that mean in simple English or simple terms? It means if you take a cat.
Benjamin Houghton: and you move its face around an image, it, like, it still knows it's a cat. Like, it doesn't matter where you put it, you can flip it upside down, you can rotate it, it still knows it's a cat, right? That's what that means, and that's kind of why CNNs are so strong, and they… they are, and will continue to be… continue to have a very important role to play in computer vision.
Benjamin Houghton: But, that's not to say that transformers don't have strengths as well.
Benjamin Houghton: So, some of the weaknesses of just a basic CNN, the limited receptive field. Remember, that's the reason why we talked about feature pyramid networks, and we talked about feature fusion.
Benjamin Houghton: And that's why UNET is designed the way it is, this idea of trying to get around one of the limitations, or one of the bottlenecks of CNNs, is this receptive field. So remember, the receptive field is how big of an area that the CNN can focus on at one time, right? So, when you do a convolution.
Benjamin Houghton: you're only looking at one small portion of the image, right? Even if you downsampled it multiple times and your image is reduced from, say.
Benjamin Houghton: let's say, originally they might be 224 by 224, down to something that's as small as 16 by 16. Even though you're looking at a large swath of the image, you're still only looking at a portion of it, right? And so you lose some of that spatial resolution.
Benjamin Houghton: they struggle with long-range dependencies. What's going on on one side of the image versus what's going on on the other side of the image? Okay, that's another, you know, and that's just the way convolutions work. And they require very careful architectural design. To an extent, I mean.
Benjamin Houghton: You know, it's not to say that all deep learning is… and you could say that… you could say that about a lot of areas of deep learning, and just, you know, machine learning in general.
Benjamin Houghton: But, yeah, so ResNet Feature Pyramid Network, right, I mean, it's not necessarily a limitation. These are the things that we've done to kind of, for, you know, machine learning and the science has done to kind of… to figure out, or get the most out of these architectures, right? The ResNet.
Benjamin Houghton: the residual connections and the feature fusions, okay? Oh, so… so some of the motivations for transformers, or for vision, specifically vision transformers, is this idea that we can capture global dependencies, right? If you'll remember from the attention mechanism that we simultaneously share information
Benjamin Houghton: everywhere throughout whatever we're attending to. So typically, like, the de facto example is going to be language-based for a transformer, right? So, when I say.
Benjamin Houghton: the… you guys remember my example, probably, the dog went to the park and barked at cats, right? Some of you haven't had that lecture, don't know what I'm talking about, but that's an example I use a lot, right? And the idea is that
Benjamin Houghton: the dog that went to the park and cat, the word cat, can simultaneously share information across the sentence. So imagine now, instead of a sentence, or a paragraph, or a book, we have an image. And the idea is that we can share information via the attention mechanism the same way. And the only thing to really figure out is
Benjamin Houghton: instead of embedding words, we're gonna embed images. That's really the only difference.
Benjamin Houghton: between the way a transformer works that you've seen before with language tasks versus the way a transformer works with vision tasks, all right? So, not to, you know, that's a little sneak peek, right? So,
Benjamin Houghton: reduced inductive bias compared to CNNs, right? So CNNs have a strong bias towards translation increments, and locality, but,
Benjamin Houghton: not so much with transformers. So, potential for unified architectures across modalities. So this is kind of a big one that we'll see a lot, right? Like, this is a pretty interesting idea, that we can basically have a unified architecture, meaning one model, that consumes multiple sources of information. We'll see that when we get to the multimodal week.
Benjamin Houghton: here in a few weeks, or whenever it is, we'll see how we can embed both images and text, and have them attend to each other, right? Which is a pretty cool idea, which is the way the modern… a lot of the, you know, that's kind of state-of-the-art for a lot of the
Benjamin Houghton: multimodal tasks, right? So, you can't do that with just a CN architecture, right? You need transformer architecture to do something like that.
Benjamin Houghton: What else? So, that's a big one. That's probably the most important, maybe, right, is the potential for the unified architecture, especially in the world we live in today.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, and then, you know, just like it makes sense, like, you know, it's just practical, right? You know, the way information and data is shared across the internet nowadays.
Benjamin Houghton: And then, finally, better scaling properties with data and model size. You know, whatever, I don't…
Benjamin Houghton: I could argue against that one as well. I would say CNNs are very efficient at what they do. Transformers get, like, very top-heavy very fast, in the sense, like, you need, like… they're… they're like a, you know, they're kind of like a Ferrari, so to speak, right? Or an F1 car, right? Like.
Benjamin Houghton: it takes a lot to get them going, but once they get going, they get going, right? You know, they do. Whereas, like, you know, CNN's like a trusty old F-150, you know, sorry for my…
Benjamin Houghton: my metaphors, but, you know, that's… they just kind of work, right? They're low maintenance, they're easy to maintain. I guess what this is saying is that, like, once you do get a transformer going, it can be really powerful, and it can scale to, like.
Benjamin Houghton: huge tasks, as we know, as we've seen, like, in the modern advancements, like, in machine learning, right? So…
Benjamin Houghton: here's a little diagram to kind of get you thinking, about, like, how this is gonna work, or not necessarily how it works, but, like, thinking about… this is kind of like what I already said, just in… as far as how information is shared.
Benjamin Houghton: across the data. This is just a diagram of that. I already said that previously, but this is kind of, like, how it would work, right? Like, when we… we have, like, an image here, and this little purple box, this is our… say this is our receptive field for our… for our CNN.
Benjamin Houghton: And, you know, that's, like, the portion of the image that we're analyzing with our CNN or our convolution operation. We see that it's just, like, one small portion of
Benjamin Houghton: above the image, right? And… Basically, this…
Benjamin Houghton: little feature map, all it does is, all it does is encode the cat, the cat's face. That's the only information it encodes, and it's all it will really ever encode. That's the way this was designed to work.
Benjamin Houghton: But we can go to a feature, a vector, right? And so now, you know, we're going to think about these vectors, right? So, you know, we're going to basically split this image up into a bunch of series of vectors, that's the way it's going to work. And this one particular vector, right.
Benjamin Houghton: started out as the image, you know, it started out as a cat, right? So you remember
Benjamin Houghton: Go back to my example.
Benjamin Houghton: the dog went to the park and barked at cats. The word dog starts off as just the word dog, but as it…
Benjamin Houghton: progresses through the transformer, it begins to encode other information into the meeting. So it's not no longer just the dog, but it's a dog that went to the park and barked at cats. It literally knows, or encodes information of other words in the sentence. That's the way transformers work, that's the way the attention mechanism works. It's the same thing here.
Benjamin Houghton: The cat's face started off as a face, but then it encodes other information from the image, like the parrot's face, and
Benjamin Houghton: whatever that is, like the cat's tail, like other parts of the image, right? And it kind of has a broader understanding of what the image is, right? I mean, that's a very simplest, overly simplistic explanation, but that's the power of the transformer and the attention mechanism, right? It can encode
Benjamin Houghton: whatever it thinks is important, right?
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, so any questions so far?
Benjamin Houghton: Are we, like, okay with the idea of the attention mechanism encoding other pieces of the data? Does that make sense to you guys? Like, I know some of you haven't had that, like, have that, like, a background in transformers, or maybe haven't studied it before, but if there's any questions, like, you know, please stop me.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay. Right. So… but that's the basic idea, like, you don't necessarily need to know Howard does it?
Benjamin Houghton: But just know that that… and I promise you I can… I can show you exactly how it… how it works, mechanically, but…
Benjamin Houghton: And in CNN, those features only encode that portion of the image. In a transformer, we can encode portions of the entire image, right? So we'll talk about how that works.
Benjamin Houghton: All right, so here's the paper to the vision transformer. Was there a question?
Benjamin Houghton: Oh, I thought I heard somebody ask a question, sorry.
Benjamin Houghton: Vision Transformer paper was written in 2020, which sounds pretty recently, but then you realize that transformers have only been around since 2017.
Benjamin Houghton: And it was first designed to do image classification. I don't know if they were really trying to be state-of-the-art with image classification, per se. I think it was more about the idea that, say, like, to introduce the idea of vision transformer, to say, hey, like.
Benjamin Houghton: look at these cool things we can do with it, or, you know, who knows, like, what they were thinking, right? Some of the key differences, so it's a larger model, right? So, like, you're… you're typically not gonna use, like, you're not gonna…
Benjamin Houghton: use a transformer and, like, edge out ImageNet. Like, you're not gonna… so, oh, I'm gonna beat ResNet 101 on, like, ImageNet. Like, maybe, like, but it doesn't matter. Like, ResNet is more than powerful enough
Benjamin Houghton: to solve ImageNet, right? Like, you don't need, really, a more… like, maybe you get, what, a hundredth of a percent better, if that? I don't know, like, the point is, is that…
Benjamin Houghton: you're not going to typically use a transformer to do, like, simple tasks that convolution neural networks already have solved very well, like classification of ImageNet dataset, right? So anyways, because they're larger and they require more parameters, but
Benjamin Houghton: allegedly, you will get better performance on large data sets and less performance on smaller data sets, and this is kind of probably a general trend. This isn't necessarily set in stone, right? Like, this is probably going to be very, very task-specific. Again, like, I would be very…
Benjamin Houghton: leery, and or I would be… I would question that if I saw that, like, you were trying to use a transformer to do a simple task of classification, alright? So don't read too much into that, right? We just need to understand the idea of vision transformers right now.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, better scaling behavior with model size. Again, that goes back to the thing where, like, if we have, like, a massive task, sure, like, transformers can scale to do some pretty wild stuff, like, as we've seen with large language models.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright, so when do you use it? Large data sets, strong computation… if you have a lot of computational resources, the need for transfer learning, robustness requirements. I mean.
Benjamin Houghton: There's gonna be other… you know, this might not be an end-all, be-all list, it's just a list. I think that most times.
Benjamin Houghton: you know, I don't want to say that there… you don't want to use one for this task, but it's not…
Benjamin Houghton: This is just, like.
Benjamin Houghton: this is just… we're talking about just classification, and they have a lot more capabilities than just doing classification. All right, so let's talk about the… the… the vision transformer architecture.
Benjamin Houghton: So what is new, the DIT concept? What is reused is the transformer concept, which is just, like, meaning the attention mechanism, right? So, really, at the end of the day, all we needed to do is figure out how to, like, embed our images and get them into the right shapes that a transformer expects, and then we're, like, off and running, right?
Benjamin Houghton: So, image patch embedding. So this is kind of… this is kind of where it starts, right? This is…
Benjamin Houghton: Not the… the only…
Benjamin Houghton: this is not the only portion that matters, but this is a big part of it, right? So, image embedding. So, what we're gonna do is we're gonna divide the image up, I mean, as simple as that, into 16… 16 by 16 grid, right? It doesn't have to be that size, but, it's probably what the paper used, this is probably why I wrote that there, okay?
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, and so once we… once we split an image up, we can just flatten it.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? So now we have vectors. And so, that's very similar So what we have…
Benjamin Houghton: That's… that's pretty much almost a one-to-one mapping, what we would use for a language transformer.
Benjamin Houghton: Right, so… Let's do this.
Benjamin Houghton: Right, so… We have a sentence.
Benjamin Houghton: Right?
Benjamin Houghton: The red dog.
Benjamin Houghton: like Clifford, right? That's gonna get one hot encoded into some vector, right, that looks like this.
Benjamin Houghton: It's gonna be, like, 0, 0…
Benjamin Houghton: 0, 1, 0, right? And then it's gonna be 0, 1, something like this, right? It's just one hot encoded, where each one of these columns represents a… represents a… a word, right? And then, after we take this, so this will… we'll say this is the one hot encoded vector. I guess I need one more vector for the dog.
Benjamin Houghton: Actually, let's do it.
Benjamin Houghton: So, this word literally represents the word the.
Benjamin Houghton: This word literally represents red, and this one represents dog, right? And as you remember, we take the one hot encoded vector.
Benjamin Houghton: And we just do matrix multiplication times some embedding matrix, usually
Benjamin Houghton: some weight matrix, and it's just a matrix multiplication, and out pops the other side is our feature vector, right? And it's gonna be…
Benjamin Houghton: usually the embedding space, I can't remember exactly, but it's usually something like 2… usually it's something like 512, so this will be, like, 512 features.
Benjamin Houghton: And this will be 3, right?
Benjamin Houghton: for one for each word, if you remember, right? And so, this is just a bunch of features, X1, X2, X3, and all we've done here is vectorize… like, you guys should be familiar with this if you've seen natural… integral language processing, right? So, that's how you encode
Benjamin Houghton: words into computers.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? You just turn them into vectors. And each one of these features kind of represents some information about that word, right? The word cat and the word dog, one of their features, let's say X412, might be the feature for pet.
Benjamin Houghton: So they both have a strong… a high value for that. Whatever it may be, whatever the computer or the model thinks it's important to encode.
Benjamin Houghton: So, all we've got to do is get our images into that shape, and we're done.
Benjamin Houghton: So… This is…
Benjamin Houghton: Wish I could erase all this at once.
Benjamin Houghton: Let's draw a diagram for this, but…
Benjamin Houghton: I don't think I have a good one drawn for this, for images, so you'll have to bear with me.
Benjamin Houghton: So… Now, instead of words in a sentence, we have an image.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? And like I said, we can just split this image up into a grid pattern.
Benjamin Houghton: And now, you know, I'm gonna put numbers in them.
Benjamin Houghton: I'm gonna label them 5, 6, you know, on, so on and so forth, and the number 16, right? And now, instead of…
Benjamin Houghton: Words, one, you know, 16 words, one after another, we just have 16 little images.
Benjamin Houghton: And so, we'll take the first part, this first one, and let's say it's a 4x4 box. This little box is 4x4 pixels, so it has 16 total pixels. We can just stretch it out, and now our vector has
Benjamin Houghton: 16, right? All the way out to X16. So now, what I've done is I've just…
Benjamin Houghton: shown you that I can take the image, and I can reshape it to match exactly
Benjamin Houghton: the way the transformer works for languages. So now we can put this directly in to a transformer, and it's going to apply the attention mechanism, right? And so, what does that mean? When you apply the attention mechanism.
Benjamin Houghton: Each one of these images are gonna… each one of these little patches are gonna share information about what's going on in their patch, and so they'll have a global and a local understanding, right? Going back to my example, the dog that went to the park and barked at cats.
Benjamin Houghton: Well, the dog at first is just a dog. It doesn't know about what else is going on in the sentence, but it applies the attention mechanism, and it knows, oh, I'm next to this other word, cat, and this other word, bark. Oh, I'm a dog that went to the park and barked at cats, because it encodes all the information. Remember, that's the way the attention mechanism works. It just shares… the feature vectors just share information.
Benjamin Houghton: Via the attention mechanism, okay? I know it's hand-wavy, but again, I'll point you guys to how the attention mechanism works.
Benjamin Houghton: So…
Benjamin Houghton: once we've done that, there's… we're pretty much more or less done. Like, we can do… now we can do a vision transformer. All we need to do is kind of handle the outputs, right? So let's look at that now.
Benjamin Houghton: or we'll go back to the notes and make sure I didn't miss anything. But that's kind of the overall idea here.
Benjamin Houghton: So…
Benjamin Houghton: Alright, that's what the… the image passion bedding means, though. We…
Benjamin Houghton: split it up, we flatten each part, and we do a linear projection to some embedding dimension, right? So embedding dimension, that… what does that mean? That's just like before, where we take a one hot encoded vector, multiply it by an embedding matrix. Now, instead of a one hot encoding vector… one hot encoded vector, it's gonna be a vector of pixels.
Benjamin Houghton: that we're gonna multiply by an embedding matrix, right? Which is, again.
Benjamin Houghton: just the normal matrix multiplication, right? It's a… it's a linear feed-forward style operation, right? Just like we've seen before.
Benjamin Houghton: We do that, and then we do the one last thing that we can't… that transformers always need. We add in the position, right? The position embeddings.
Benjamin Houghton: Why do we do that?
Benjamin Houghton: Well, because the order of the rows in the matrix is not embedded in the mathematics, right?
Benjamin Houghton: If you put a row and a column in different locations, their product is still the same.
Benjamin Houghton: Meaning that a row in, let's say, row 2 times, say, column 3,
Benjamin Houghton: their inner product is identical, whether they're in… no matter what position they're in. So I can move row 2 down to row 4, and I can move column 3 over to column 1. When they multiply together, they're the same number.
Benjamin Houghton: there's no positional information embedded in them, it's just the way we've stored the information in the computer. But the computer's not aware that
Benjamin Houghton: that they're in a certain position, per se, right? Does that… that makes sense. That information is not encoded into the… into the vectors.
Benjamin Houghton: And so you encode that information via the positional embeddings, just like we did in transformers, and so then we're done, right? We have all the information we need to go into the transformer encoder, which then performs the multi-headed self-attention layers, just like you've seen.
Benjamin Houghton: before, the feed-forward, and then we do some feed-forward layers, we do our layer normalization, residual connection. So everything… the transformer encoder is identical, right? There's nothing that's really changed.
Benjamin Houghton: There is one small caveat.
Benjamin Houghton: To this, Now, remember when we do a transformer, what is… what is the output
Benjamin Houghton: what does the output look like, right? So…
Benjamin Houghton: when we… when we run a transformer, the output is, for every token in, we get a token out. Remember, that's… that's kind of the way they work.
Benjamin Houghton: And remember, it's the next word token, right? Remember we put… when we do Transformers, we put the entire sentence in at once, all the tokens? The big, the dog went to the bark, parked and barked at cats.
Benjamin Houghton: all those tokens go into them, and each token, each row, its job is to predict the next token, right? So we simultaneously predict the next word for the entire matrix, or the entire sentence, remember?
Benjamin Houghton: So, it works the same way here.
Benjamin Houghton: So, what are we gonna get out of this? Well, if we have 16 patches in, we're going to get 16 whatever out, right? Whatever that represents. So, we have this special, class token that we add to the beginning of, instead of just
Benjamin Houghton: you know, it's just… remember we had the beginning, the begin token, or start a sentence token? It's kind of like that. It's just a special token, and that vector's job is to…
Benjamin Houghton: You know, it's, you know, it… so it'll be that vector, the class vector token, and then it'll be all the… all the image patches, 1 through 16.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay? And so, they're all going to be sharing information, and the class token, or the class vector, well, its job is to kind of figure out, is to learn
Benjamin Houghton: basically gather information from all the other vectors and make the final class prediction. Remember, we're doing a classification task in this original paper.
Benjamin Houghton: So why is it done that way, right? So…
Benjamin Houghton: The reason it's done this way is because
Benjamin Houghton: It wouldn't make sense… like, you could always… you could think about it like this. Well, what if we just always used the same… the first… the first step? What if we always just paid attention to the first…
Benjamin Houghton: the first patch. Like, we use… remember, it's going to be 16 tokens out. Well, it's actually going to be 17. It'll be token 0, plus the other 16 patches, or whatever, however many patches. This diagram, I know it only has 10… it only has 9 image patches.
Benjamin Houghton: And they're… but I think the paper, they used 16, but this is 3x3, so I'll… we'll use this example, right? This only has 9 image patches, then it has that class, so it's going to get 10 whatever out, right? That… we're basically gonna throw away 1 through 9, and we're only going to pay attention to the first position, or the first token.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? Or the first patch embedding.
Benjamin Houghton: If you… let's say we didn't do that, and we just used one of the random… one of the nines. It doesn't really matter which one, you know, it's… the model would implicitly learn which one to pay attention to, and it would, you know, through back propagation, if we only penalized it for one of them.
Benjamin Houghton: It would kind of learn that. But the problem is, is that every single time that initial patch changes.
Benjamin Houghton: it's gonna change, right? It's better to, you could also do something like global pooling. There's a bunch of ways you could do it, but the authors say that, you know, you know, it's better to have, like, this learn… and this is a learned embedding, right? This class token. This class token will get multiplied by some… by some embedding matrix as well.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? Just like the other tokens. In its job, it learns to… how to efficiently gather the information it needs from the other… from the other 9 patches in this example.
Benjamin Houghton: So, you take that, and you put that portion, that particular vector, into an MLP,
Benjamin Houghton: Meaning multi-layer perceptron or a feed board layer, and it does the final classification.
Benjamin Houghton: And so that's it. Well, I guess there's one more thing.
Benjamin Houghton: The transformer encoder here.
Benjamin Houghton: There's a little diagram, just look at that real fast. It looks the same to me. Embedding patches, you do a normalization layer, multi-headed attention, you have the residual connection, which has the arrow coming, so this is the residual connection here.
Benjamin Houghton: this portion, residual connection, normalization, multi-layer perceptron, and then normal, and then another residual connection. So that's a very standard, straightforward, what you would see transformer block.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright.
Benjamin Houghton: And you… this… or… and you might do this, and more accurately, it's an encoder, right? There's no cross-attention, right? Which, we will talk about a decoder, you know, we will use the… we will want to understand how decoders work, because we, like, that's…
Benjamin Houghton: We can attend to, you know, we can do 10 vision to…
Benjamin Houghton: There's different ways of doing it, but, you know, you can imagine a scenario where you can start to think about, now that you've seen this, like, this opens up a lot of possibilities, right? So you could encode images, and then you could encode text.
Benjamin Houghton: And then you could have the text attend to the… to the images in the decoder, and then generate more text. Like, that's kind of how multi-modal models work, right? We've just got to get our gate into the right shape.
Benjamin Houghton: run it through the attention mechanism, and have it attend to whatever we want to have it attend to. In this example, it's images attending to images, but it doesn't have to be images to images. It could be images to text, text to other images, or whatever you could possibly think of, right? As long as it fits
Benjamin Houghton: into the attention mechanism. And you've kind of, like, built out the appropriate framework or little nuances you need, like the class token or whatever in this particular example.
Benjamin Houghton: Questions on this?
Benjamin Houghton: Is it a natural extension from Transformers to you?
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah.
Benjamin Houghton: What do you guys think, yeah?
Benjamin Houghton: You guys are quiet back there. Any questions?
Benjamin Houghton: I know that this is… I'm challenging you, because I'm asking you to, like.
Benjamin Houghton: Just trust me that the attention mechanism works, and just focus on, like, what we're trying to accomplish.
Benjamin Houghton: And it might be kind of abstract.
Benjamin Houghton: Yep.
Benjamin Houghton: Absolutely.
Benjamin Houghton: The attention mechanism?
Benjamin Houghton: Well, the best thing to do…
Benjamin Houghton: Which is… I'm glad you asked that, because,
Benjamin Houghton: this will be good for the rest of the class as well. So, you'll want to go to the centralized lecture Content. You guys are all familiar with this by now, right? This website? This is, Professor James's website, right?
Benjamin Houghton: And you'll see here, if you go to Machine Learning, and then to Deep Learning.
Benjamin Houghton: This is the lectures you're going to want to pay attention to.
Benjamin Houghton: is the transformers, okay? So, and specifically,
Benjamin Houghton: This one, the Transformers Introduction.
Benjamin Houghton: So, what did you want to see?
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah.
Benjamin Houghton: Absolutely.
Benjamin Houghton: It's added quite a bit to this, actually.
Benjamin Houghton: So…
Benjamin Houghton: you have, like, these query key and values, right? Remember that?
Benjamin Houghton: So… Yeah, we're starting to get pretty, pretty deep into it, right? But, essentially.
Benjamin Houghton: The way the attention… and this is probably the…
Benjamin Houghton: this is the encoder self-attention. Right, this is probably a good, good, like, overall, like, general example, right? So…
Benjamin Houghton: the encoder self-attention, right? So we have X, like, what is… what is X? So X is going to be your input to your intention, your attention layer, your encoder. In this particular case, X would be an… would be a embedded image.
Benjamin Houghton: Or, I'm sorry, in this lecture, it's referring to, like, language, but it doesn't really explicitly say. It could be whatever you've embedded. So X is just your image patches, or it could be your words that you embedded into… in your embedding space via
Benjamin Houghton: your embedding matrix, like, you take your one hot encoded words, you multiply them by your embedding matrix, and then you have… you have your embedded… you have your… your features. X is just your features. It's also the output of other previous layers, right? So it's just whatever the input is
Benjamin Houghton: Into the… into the transformer block. And it's just gonna be a matrix, where typically, each row.
Benjamin Houghton: It's gonna represent a word.
Benjamin Houghton: Or an image patch.
Benjamin Houghton: And it's gonna be a row of words, or it's gonna be rows of words, so it would be, like, the dog went to the park and barked at cats.
Benjamin Houghton: And then it's going to be features, right? Each word is going to have some set of features, or they're all gonna have the same features, usually 512.
Benjamin Houghton: And that's going to encode each word. So for images, though, it's going to be, like, the 16 or the 9 patches, however many patches you will have, right?
Benjamin Houghton: that have been multiplied by some embedding matrix, alright? So that's…
Benjamin Houghton: Well, how you get X? You multiply… now, the learned parameters of a transformer, if you remember, is going to be this W, Q, W, K, and WV, the query, the key, and the value.
Benjamin Houghton: Right.
Benjamin Houghton: So the query is what I need to know, and the key is kind of… remember, the key is… the query is, like, the information I need to know that vector wants.
Benjamin Houghton: the key is the information that that vector has, and the value is just the value of that information, right? So, you do the matrix multiplication bid between the query and the key.
Benjamin Houghton: And, basically.
Benjamin Houghton: vectors or words that have high cosine similarity mean that, hey, I'm a query, or you're a key that has a lot of information I need, so I'm going to pay attention to you, right?
Benjamin Houghton: And then…
Benjamin Houghton: Once you do the query times key multiplication, if you get a vector that has a high… that has a,
Benjamin Houghton: a high similarity. When you do the final multiplication.
Benjamin Houghton: of the query key product times the value, you'll take more information from that vector. So that's, like, a very, very high-level overview, obviously, right? Like, that's a…
Benjamin Houghton: quite a bit, like, normally I'd take an hour to explain that, and I did it in, like, 5 minutes, but does that help, you remember?
Benjamin Houghton: Right, so the attention… remember that this is the attention, the attention equation. So up here, attention is equal to the softmax of the query times key transpose.
Benjamin Houghton: Over the dimensionality of
Benjamin Houghton: The key, or you remember… and that's just… that's how you normalize it, and then you multiply by the value.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright, there's lots of,
Benjamin Houghton: other visualizations here, telling you, like, how the information, like, kind of encodes, right? Again, probably better off, if you want to know about this in detail, to watch the video. Like, from a high level, like, this is what we're trying to create, like, this is what the attention mechanism does. It… it takes…
Benjamin Houghton: imagine, like, instead of the words being a list, imagine, like, they're all kind of, like, around a circle here I have, and a campfire, I don't know, and they're all, like, sharing information freely, right? And the intention mechanism is going to
Benjamin Houghton: Do it systematically, mathematically, and learn how to, like, which words should share information and how much information, right?
Benjamin Houghton: So that's what we're trying to do conceptually. If you don't remember how it works, like, you should, like, if that wasn't enough of an explanation, hopefully it was, you should really watch, like, the Transformer videos or something else, right?
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, so, and honestly, most of you who have, like, taken deep learning, like, you should really probably watch Professor James' video, because he's gonna give you a different perspective than I gave you as well, right? And you've probably seen… I've talked about it quite a bit with you guys.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay.
Benjamin Houghton: Any questions on that?
Benjamin Houghton: Anything else about vision transformers, or, so, so far, like, what we've talked about so far, or the attention mechanism.
Benjamin Houghton: Did I catch you guys off guard, like, coming in here and talking about Transformers today? You guys weren't ready for it?
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, good.
Benjamin Houghton: Nice.
Benjamin Houghton: You're well… you're ready. So you're ready for it then, basically. Nice.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, so, time series, that's a good point. I mean.
Benjamin Houghton: like, language and time series are very synonymous, right? Meaning that we can think of words in a sentence as a set of… as really time series data, right? Like, it's this temporal understanding, right? Words…
Benjamin Houghton: when you jumble them up, have no meaning, right? But when they're in the right specific order, they have meaning. Just like a lot of other time series data, it's like akin to, like, taking temperature data and, like, jumbling it all up, it's just randomness. But when you put temperature data in order, we know, oh, it was hot this day, and
Benjamin Houghton: cold, and we see a seasonal pattern, and whatever else, like, you can tell a whole story from it. Same thing with… with words, right? They have… order has meaning, and, you know, some of you have taken the time series.
Benjamin Houghton: You know, I've actually given a lecture in Dr. Perna's class as well, in Time Series, about, you know, using
Benjamin Houghton: these types of architectures for time series as well, right? And it's a pretty natural extension to time series data as well.
Benjamin Houghton: I mean, it's basically the same thing.
Benjamin Houghton: Yes.
Benjamin Houghton: What's that?
Benjamin Houghton: So… Yeah, so…
Benjamin Houghton: they were talking about their… how they were relating Transformers to Time Series, and I was saying that… what I was saying is that
Benjamin Houghton: Language is very akin to time series data, and
Benjamin Houghton: it's very easy, or it's kind of natural to go back and forth and use time series data or language data with transformers. I wasn't connecting at all to images. However.
Benjamin Houghton: when we start talking about videos, there is a temporal component. And the fact that we can use the attention mechanism over time is gonna play into why transformers have become, very recently, kind of very, I'd say.
Benjamin Houghton: But, pretty recently have become kind of the state-of-the-art in object tracking.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? Because they can do something that other architectures cannot.
Benjamin Houghton: And that's kind of, like, understand stuff through time, and how, like, this frame relates to this frame. And they do it via the attention mechanism.
Benjamin Houghton: Right, and so that's why I wanted to talk about this today, because I've had a feeling that if I went and started saying, like, I'd be two steps ahead instead of just, like, one, right? Because, like, I know you guys might need to go back and kind of review attention mechanism, but it might have been really difficult if I said, okay.
Benjamin Houghton: you know, you need to know what the attention mechanism is, and you need to know how it applies images. Then we can talk about object detection with transformers, right?
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah.
Benjamin Houghton: I know, it's a lot, but, like, this is kind of, like, we're starting to get to, like, the…
Benjamin Houghton: you know, this is some of the most advanced stuff you're gonna, like, that we're gonna talk about, you know, it's pretty advanced topics, I think, right?
Benjamin Houghton: for machine learning. We're not just, like, classifying pictures of dogs and cats anymore, right?
Benjamin Houghton: Alright.
Benjamin Houghton: Applications! So, image classification, right, object detection.
Benjamin Houghton: So we'll talk about object detection today.
Benjamin Houghton: Not object tracking, but object detection.
Benjamin Houghton: the, the DT… DETR, right? And we just talked about object detection previously, in the previous week, so it's a good time. Semantic segmentation, we're not going to get into that, but just know it exists, right? And then video… video understanding. One thing that's not written here is,
Benjamin Houghton: is object tracking, right? Like, like I said, this has been a pretty, you know, pretty recent development, right?
Benjamin Houghton: So, we'll definitely talk about that as well.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright, we talked already about some of these advantages and limitations. We'll just read the high points again. The global processing, right? We can…
Benjamin Houghton: doesn't matter where two patches or pixels are in an image, they can share information through that long-range dependency, via the attention mechanism. Scalability, right, we talked about that. Flexibility.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? So, that really gets down to, like, the unified architecture across various tasks and modalities. Yes.
Benjamin Houghton: It's very… yeah, vision transformers are typically gonna be more computationally They're gonna acquire more…
Benjamin Houghton: Horse… yeah, they're gonna be more…
Benjamin Houghton: basically require more computations to perform typically the same task. So…
Benjamin Houghton: The attention mechanism inherently is a… N squared… operation.
Benjamin Houghton: So the attention mechanism, in order for every word, or every pixel, or whatever it is to attend to every other word, or every other pixel, it requires one computation. So that's why, in big O notation, the attention mechanism is typically N squared. We talk about that quite a bit.
Benjamin Houghton: The majority of what you see today, like, that is kind of, like, where all of the research is, and or… not necessarily the research, but the innovation is right now.
Benjamin Houghton: The reason why we have ChatGPT and all those other models is because they have figured out a way to get around that, right? So, basically.
Benjamin Houghton: transformers with N squared or big O notation isn't gonna get you very far, right? It's gonna get you to, like, you know, 2018, 2019 levels. But we've… since, like, the community and the research… the…
Benjamin Houghton: has long since surpassed that limitation, right? So, understanding that
Benjamin Houghton: that the attention mechanism inherently is a very computationally expensive mechanism is going to serve you well. Like, you need to always keep that in mind and wonder, like, how exactly are you going to get around that, right? Or maybe you don't need to, right? If you only have 512 words in your sentence, it doesn't really matter.
Benjamin Houghton: or 16 images, patches, it doesn't really matter. But if you want to do object tracking.
Benjamin Houghton: across thousands of frames, and you have to have every single frame attend to every other frame, it's not gonna work. It's gonna break down. So you need to figure out a way around that. Like, maybe just ignore the old frames, maybe you use a different type of attention mechanism that, like, you know, there's other versions that
Benjamin Houghton: you know.
Benjamin Houghton: we're starting to get into, like, large language modeling ideas and techniques, but you know, you're not going to want to attend to basically every single, every single term, right? Okay.
Benjamin Houghton: So, that's a great question, though. So yeah, like, the… absolutely,
Benjamin Houghton: You know, they do scale well with the right enhancements, though, okay?
Benjamin Houghton: Limitations, computational requirements, right? I said that before, quadratic complexity with sequence length. That's that N squared big O notation.
Benjamin Houghton: high memory usage, yeah, data requirements, and then architecture constraints, alright? Okay,
Benjamin Houghton: Let's see, it's… Detection, transform, I think we'll,
Benjamin Houghton: 423… yeah, let's, let's take a…
Benjamin Houghton: No, not even an hour. You know, we'll go for a little while longer, then we'll take a break. We'll start the…
Benjamin Houghton: SAR detection transformers, take a break here in a little bit.
Benjamin Houghton: We have our spotlight presentation and a quiz today, so, you know, around probably 6 o'clock,
Benjamin Houghton: I'm sorry, around… not 6 o'clock, around 5.30ish, we'll need to tran… to kind of transition to that, maybe a little bit before.
Benjamin Houghton: Maybe, like, 515.
Benjamin Houghton: So… We'll go for about another 10 minutes to take a break, I think.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright, detection transformers.
Benjamin Houghton: So, the Vision Transformer architecture is specialized for object detection, and
Benjamin Houghton: It emerged as an alternative to CNN-based detectors, so you can combine transformers with a global attention detection test, and this was first introduced in detection… the DETR detection transformers in 2020. So you're not, like, you're not gonna, like, read this paper, and you're not gonna, like, just
Benjamin Houghton: beat out YOLO and faster RCNN. Typically, those models have been, like… YOLO, especially… yeah, especially YOLO, has been, like, perfected, per se, right? It's had iteration after iteration, they more or less perfected it.
Benjamin Houghton: Same thing with DETR. It's not been, maybe, specialized to the same level that YOLO has, but, like.
Benjamin Houghton: Typically, when you're doing real-time detection.
Benjamin Houghton: it's gonna be tough to beat YOLO, right? But this is just, like, a starting place. Like, this is the first iteration. This is YOLO V1 of the transformer detections, right? So it's a good place to start, and a good model to understand. Even though you're not, in practice, would never use this particular model, you would maybe use some iteration of it if you wanted to, right?
Benjamin Houghton: But this is, like, the grandfather to them all, just like how we talked about YOLA, right?
Benjamin Houghton: So, let's talk about it. Some of the architecture. So it's a transformer, encoder, decoder, backbone.
Benjamin Houghton: with a CNN feature extraction, right? So, you're typically going to have
Benjamin Houghton: I think that this is…
Benjamin Houghton: Not sure why I wrote it like that, right? So that doesn't make any sense.
Benjamin Houghton: I apologize. This should say…
Benjamin Houghton: there's a transformer encoder, decoder, but there's not a backbone, right? The CNN feature extraction is the backbone. So you're still going to have a CNN backbone. I have to fix this. But you'll have, like, an end-to-end trainable design. Remember with, like, faster RCNN, we had, like, multiple networks? We had… it was, like, quasi-unified. I mean, YOLO is a unified network.
Benjamin Houghton: But remember that, with Faster RCNN, we had to have that pesky feature pyramid… I'm sorry, not pet…
Benjamin Houghton: That pesky, region proposal network that had to tell us where to look, and then we looked, right?
Benjamin Houghton: Remember, we had to look twice, as opposed to yellow, we only looked once, right?
Benjamin Houghton: But it's, like, this is going to be a unified design, like that. And, some of the advantages is we'll have the global context. Remember, again, we've said this multiple times, that global context, no handcrafted components needed.
Benjamin Houghton: No simplified detection pipeline, and then, like, a natural multi-object handling, right? Which is pretty neat. So what does that mean, right? So, I mean, faster RCNN has the multi-object handling pretty easily.
Benjamin Houghton: But it's kind of a pain, because you have the re… you had the reproposal network, and you have to do non-max oppression, and then you have to do…
Benjamin Houghton: then you do the classification, and bounding box regression, and all that stuff, then you do non-max expression again, right? You'll see in a minute that the transformer architecture is kind of streamlined, or it's, like, much… kind of simplified, in a sense.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, and that's what I was… so why detection transformers that literally just said that. It does kind of simplify things quite a bit. No anchor boxes are needed, no non-max suppression, right? It's actually, in my opinion, a little bit more straightforward than… than faster RCNN, especially if you've studied transformers.
Benjamin Houghton: Performance, competitive, or better accuracy? It's debatable.
Benjamin Houghton: But they're competitive, we'll say that, especially some of the newer versions.
Benjamin Houghton: Better handling of occlusions, right? So, occlusion, remember, if something's in front of an object, the person's hiding behind a tree.
Benjamin Houghton: strong performance on crowded scenes, and flexibility, right? So, yeah. So…
Benjamin Houghton: Let's get into it. Enough about the background. Well, I guess we have this part first. So, evolution of detection transformer. So, this is what we're going to talk about today, DETR, which was written in 2020, the first successful transformer-based detector. It proved the viability of detection.
Benjamin Houghton: But it had slow convergence and struggled with small objects, alright? But…
Benjamin Houghton: there's some pretty key enhancements here, improvements to the deformable DTR, which uses… look, what do you know? Like, of course, the very first thing they did
Benjamin Houghton: you know, you were asking me, Bo, you were asking me before about, the attention mechanism, and, you know, one of the very first things they did
Benjamin Houghton: Well, my iPad is not cooperating, so actually I might have to plug it in.
Benjamin Houghton: is they use sparse attention mechanisms. So a sparse attention mechanism just means that you don't attend to every little thing. Like, you kind of pick and choose what you're going to attend to, alright?
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, so… It's kind of…
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, I'll give you an example. So basically, What that means is…
Benjamin Houghton: Very fun. For contention, right? So…
Benjamin Houghton: it just means that, like, instead of attending to every single word, you might attend to every other word, or every seventh word, or whatever, right? You'll have some pattern. There's…
Benjamin Houghton: I don't know how many papers have been written on the subject, but a lot, right? And there's all different patterns, right? You might have… you can think of it, like, almost like you have, like, local attention, so you'll attend to the words around you, and then,
Benjamin Houghton: maybe every hundredth word becomes, like, a global attention gateway, in the sense that it encodes, like, global information, right? So, you can…
Benjamin Houghton: you'll see, like, if you, like, type in, like, attention pattern… actually, let's just do it real fast, like, I, like…
Benjamin Houghton: sparse… attention… Matrix…
Benjamin Houghton: patterns… I don't know. Let's see if I… if I'm… that's what I'm thinking in my head. Yeah, this is exactly what I was looking for. So this is what they look like, right? So there's all these different patterns. So, like, along one column is one… like, imagine
Benjamin Houghton: the words in the sentence, the dog went to the park and barked at cats along the top and the bottom, and each word attends to each other… every single other word. That would be a full matrix, like a full blue matrix. But now you can have all these different patterns, right? So you can have things like, okay, we only attend to the close words, and then
Benjamin Houghton: And then there's also… oh, so this is a local attention… that's a local attention window, right? Here, this is a good one to look at. All right,
Benjamin Houghton: local, global, and random, right? So you can kind of, like, think about this… this in your head,
Benjamin Houghton: like, all these different, like, all these different random patterns, alright? So these… this is what sparse attention means. And at first, you might think, like, well, what… what good is it…
Benjamin Houghton: Like, you might have, like, some words that are, like, the global words that every other word attends to, which is kind of an interesting idea, because then all the other words will, like, share information to those, those particular vectors, or those words, and then they'll share the information down
Benjamin Houghton: to the ones that are just local. So, like, what is that… an example or metaphor would that be? It's like, if I had a group… imagine I had 100 people, and I split them into groups of 10.
Benjamin Houghton: And all the 10 people talked amongst themselves, and they all, like, shared information, all right? And then you had one person.
Benjamin Houghton: Who went outside that group, from every single other group. So, we have 10 groups.
Benjamin Houghton: Each group has 10 people, one person is selected to go and talk to the other 10 people. Maybe they're the group leaders, and they share information.
Benjamin Houghton: And then they bring it back to their group. And so… and then they tell their group what's going on outside in the other groups, right? So that's the idea of, like, the global, or, like, the…
Benjamin Houghton: I like to think of it like the anchor word, right? So that's what it means by sparked attention. And so you can share local information and global information still, right? Not to say that that's not necessarily, like, the way large language models necessarily do it, today, but, like, there's many ways to get around this. This is one of them, and that's what
Benjamin Houghton: Sparse attention means.
Benjamin Houghton: Of course, this is such a loaded topic, because there's just so much information, and so many… like, this is…
Benjamin Houghton: there's a lot in this space, right? And and so…
Benjamin Houghton: don't think you need to understand all this. Like, you don't necessarily need to know what sparse attention is,
Benjamin Houghton: or stuff like that. I'm trying to think of some… some other, like.
Benjamin Houghton: enhancements, but I guess what I'm saying is.
Benjamin Houghton: you know, just understand the big pictures and understand, like, what's… what's out there and what to be aware of. You can always go back later and look up stuff that's important to you, right? Okay, conditional DETR content-dependent queries.
Benjamin Houghton: So, different queries for different images, right? So there's… this is another paper, and we're not going to get really into the details on these. We're really going to focus on… on DETR, right? Okay, so…
Benjamin Houghton: So this was introduced by Facebook in, 2020.
Benjamin Houghton: And I just realized it's probably a good place to stop, honestly, so…
Benjamin Houghton: We'll stop here, let's take a break, and…
Benjamin Houghton: come back. It's 4.34, we'll resume at 4.44, and we'll talk about DETR, and this is the last portion of the lecture, and then we'll… we'll be… we'll be done with this. We'll do our spotlight presentation.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright.
Benjamin Houghton: So, we will resume where we left off on detection transformer. So…
Benjamin Houghton: Like I said before, this was the first detection transformer. There has since been iterations of this.
Benjamin Houghton: From a high-level concept.
Benjamin Houghton: it kind of re… it does reframe the object detection as a direct set of prediction problem, right? It… it goes… you know, you have an image input, and you have predictions output. You don't have, like, non-max suppression, or region proposal networks, or any of that stuff. It uses the… it does use the inter… the transformer, encoder, decoder architecture.
Benjamin Houghton: Predicts fixed-size objects in parallel.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? So that's very much like a transformer architecture. What does that mean? That means that you always have the same number of objects. It's kind of like YOLO in that sense. Like, remember in YOLO, we gridded out an image, and, we had, like, always would have, like, two… each box would get two objects. It's the same thing with transformers. Like, ahead of time, you have to set that, how many objects you're gonna…
Benjamin Houghton: detect, because remember I said before,
Benjamin Houghton: it's like, the number of inputs is the number of outputs. So, if you have 16…
Benjamin Houghton: image patches in, you'll have 16 out. If you have, 100, 512 words, you'll have 512 words out, right? That's also known as, the context length, right, in, that space as well, right? It's how many things you can attend to at one time, essentially.
Benjamin Houghton: Right, so, this is the traditional approach.
Benjamin Houghton: won't spend a lot of time on this, because we just talked about this, right? Does anybody know what diagram is that?
Benjamin Houghton: pop question.
Benjamin Houghton: What model is that from? Yes.
Benjamin Houghton: faster, or…
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, good job. Yeah, it's faster RTNN. You can tell because that's the Region Proposal Network, remember? That's the key innovation in Faster RTNN, is the Region Proposal Network.
Benjamin Houghton: Cool. So anyways, this is, like, kind of the traditional approach, aka… I mean, it is still, like, it says traditional, like, it's a bad thing, but that's not necessarily the case, right? But there are some limitations. So, non-differential components, right? You can't do…
Benjamin Houghton: You cannot… there's no learn parameters with non-max oppression, right? So you can't differentiate that, you can't backpropagate through it, you can't train a network on that. Anchor box assignment rules.
Benjamin Houghton: Post-processing, let's see. There's a lot of manual design, so anchor box sizes.
Benjamin Houghton: non-max suppression thresholds, feature pyramid design, right? There's a lot… I mean.
Benjamin Houghton: this last one isn't really fair, per se, because, you might use a feature pyramid network anyways with a vision transformer or backbone, right? So that's not…
Benjamin Houghton: however, one of the things that Transformers can do better
Benjamin Houghton: then, faster RCNN is they have this global awareness, as you know, so the, you know, the feature pyramid network isn't as important, right? Remember we talked about how, like, we might use different levels of the pyramid to do predictions for large objects and small objects? That's not going to be as critical with a vision transformer.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright, so here is the… the diagram, right? So,
Benjamin Houghton: Let's understand the inputs and outputs real fast. So, an image goes in to the CNN, the backbone?
Benjamin Houghton: Right? You get some… you get some features, and like, as the authors of this paper have so elegantly drawn, they flatten them into this rectangle here, right? That represents, like, our flattened features, I guess, okay?
Benjamin Houghton: So we have our features, we flatten them into patches, basically, and then each patch attends to every other patch in the transformer, right? In the transformer, encoder, decoder, and
Benjamin Houghton: we take that output, and we feed it into, it's gonna be, like, typically gonna be a, you know, you'll have some beadboard layer, right, in this box. It's not drawn here. We'll see more detail in a second. And you'll have, basically.
Benjamin Houghton: your output is going to be some vector, right? So here, n is 100, meaning your output of this model is going to be a vector of 100. It's going to be of 100 predictions, right? And then each… it's not going to be 100 elements, because each prediction will be,
Benjamin Houghton: You know, you can think of it as 100 rows. Remember when we do a transformer?
Benjamin Houghton: You know, your context length in is your context length out, so if you had, like, 512, which was, like, I think it was, like, the original context length, the original transformer, you would have 512 out. Here, you're gonna have 100 out, right? So you're gonna have, like, say you would have 100…
Benjamin Houghton: rows out, and each row is going to represent a bounding box, where it is, and then it's labeled, and it's, like, some prediction or some confidence associated with it, which will be important, because if you have 100 predictions.
Benjamin Houghton: you have to have some way of, like, determining, well, this is an object and this is not an object, right? And so that's what that is for, all right? So the key advantage is it is fully differentiable pipeline, like, all the way back, like, so you can back-propagate all the way from your predictions, all the way to your input, basically, right?
Benjamin Houghton: All the way through the door.
Benjamin Houghton: all the way back through the backbone, right? So, it's fully… it's a single unified loss function.
Benjamin Houghton: there's no hand-tuned parameters, and well, that's… yeah, mostly no hand-tuned parameters. There is one,
Benjamin Houghton: like, the fixed size predictions, this is gonna be a hyperparameter, right? What this is really saying is that, like, you don't have to worry about non-max oppression anymore, thresholds, you don't have to worry about, a lot of the hyperparameters that you had to deal with with faster RCNN.
Benjamin Houghton: Architectural benefits, so the global context, again, said that, like, 8 times today.
Benjamin Houghton: the natural handling of overlapping of objects, which is really nice, right?
Benjamin Houghton: It's extensible to… this works well for panoptic segmentation, and it's pretty simple implementation, right?
Benjamin Houghton: Alright, so here's a little bit more detailed diagram.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? And we can look at this, and we'll look at the encoder-decoder, and you guys will probably, hopefully, have some questions about this. First time you've seen this, right? So, first thing is the image goes into the CNN. We get our features.
Benjamin Houghton: well, and then we flatten them, right? So, step one, right, over here on the left, the image goes in.
Benjamin Houghton: to the CNN, and then the features get flattened.
Benjamin Houghton: And then, in that we add some positional embeddings. Remember, we want to get those… we want to get our features into, like, our patches, into, like,
Benjamin Houghton: basically vectors, right? So…
Benjamin Houghton: Patch 1 is a vector, patch 2 is a vector, so on and so forth, alright? Then the features go into the encoder, and they do their global context. All the patches learn about all the other patches, they do the attention mechanism.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? The output is… notice how the number of inputs is the number of outputs in this diagram, right? So whatever that is, the number of patches in is the number of patches out.
Benjamin Houghton: And then they're gonna go over to the decoder, right? And so the decoder… what's the decoder's input? Do you guys remember from, like, a traditional transformer? What is the… what is the input into the… what is the input into the decoder?
Benjamin Houghton: So this is gonna be a pretty fundamental shift, right? Like, this is a different way of thinking about it. You guys remember, like, what is the decoder input?
Benjamin Houghton: Yes, Katie.
Benjamin Houghton: perform.
Benjamin Houghton: It would be… if… so… so, give me an example, like, if,
Benjamin Houghton: if I… if I'm translating, say, from English to Spanish.
Benjamin Houghton: And I said… let's say the cat is crazy, which is Elgato Loco, right? I think in Spanish, something like that. So… and I wanted it… I'm predicting… what am I predicting, right? The next…
Benjamin Houghton: Token, remember? So what would be… what would be the first input?
Benjamin Houghton: Into the decoder, then.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, it's aka a, start of… Sort of sentence, right?
Benjamin Houghton: Right? So it would be the previous token.
Benjamin Houghton: So, the first token would be start of sequence.
Benjamin Houghton: In the first row. The next row would be… L… But for the…
Benjamin Houghton: And so the first row, the first… the first query, the first row into the decoder, start a sequence, its job is to predict the word the, or L, and then you would have the next word row down would be
Benjamin Houghton: start a sequence L for the, and its job would be to predict the token GATTO for El Gato.
Benjamin Houghton: So on and so forth. So you would have all the previous tokens. That is what the decoder's input looks like, the previous tokens. That's the way large language models work, right?
Benjamin Houghton: as a large language model generates tokens, its tokens that it generated wrap back around and become its input. So it knows, like, this is what I said, this is what I'm going to say next, right?
Benjamin Houghton: You guys remember that?
Benjamin Houghton: Completely different for this, though, right? So throw all that out, it doesn't matter here, okay, at all, right? It's gonna matter later on. That's really more of a temporal dependency
Benjamin Houghton: Pattern.
Benjamin Houghton: What we're doing here is, like, we just have random… we have what we call object queries, and these are just learned embeddings.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? They're literally just vectors, okay? They're initial… I can't remember exactly how they're initialized, it doesn't really matter. Let's just say that they're random numbers, right? So you have these random vectors, random numbers.
Benjamin Houghton: And then they're going to be multiplied by an embedding weight.
Benjamin Houghton: So instead of… normally, we take words, and we… we one-hot encode them.
Benjamin Houghton: and we multiply them by a, embedding matrix. So those are the… and those become the inputs, right? Once they've been multiplied, they've been embedded into some embedding space, those become the inputs into the decoder, into the attention mechanism. Now, it could be… I don't really know what it is, I can't really remember, it doesn't matter. It could be, like, literally.
Benjamin Houghton: The number 1 for… and then a bunch of zeros representing
Benjamin Houghton: Query 1, and then it could be query 2, or it could be random numbers. There is going to be some specific reason to initialize it a certain way, maybe I'll look it up here in a second, I don't remember exactly how they initialized it, but it's going to be some random… some vector, some arbitrary vector, that then gets multiplied by some learned weight embedding matrix.
Benjamin Houghton: it's going to get embedded, and instead of the previous tokens, it's just going to be some arbitrary vector that gets input into this matrix. Now, into this, I'm sorry, into the decoder. Now, remember that in a transformer, the previous token's job is to predict the next token, not here. Here, it's just that each
Benjamin Houghton: query, or each input, its job is to predict some object, right? So, you'll have some vector that gets input, and instead of predicting the next object, or the next token, or whatever, it's just going to predict some object.
Benjamin Houghton: And you're gonna have 100 of these, right? They don't really matter what they are, right? So they just call them object queries, right? So those are the queries, those are the inputs of the decoder.
Benjamin Houghton: They're going to attend to the output of the encoder, as you see in the diagram. They're going to do what I call
Benjamin Houghton: cross-attention, right? Well, actually, first they'll do… remember in the decoder, you do self-attention and cross-attention? So, in self-attention, all the queries will attend to each other, they'll learn about, I guess, each other, right? And then they'll attend to
Benjamin Houghton: the encoder outputs.
Benjamin Houghton: And they'll learn about what the encode… like, what's in the… they'll learn about what's in the image, and then they'll share information again via cross… via self-attention, and then they'll…
Benjamin Houghton: learn about the, encoder's outputs again, like, like you see, like, in a series, because this is kind of a very simplistic, overly simplistic drawing of a, my iPod's dead, so I'm going to use the
Benjamin Houghton: Or… last week, there was, like, literally 30 pens, and now there's not one, not one marker up here. There was literally a stack of them. Like, the people, like, I don't know what they do, like, the projector's broken one week, then they're, like, someone's playing jokes on me, like, alright, let me turn my iPad on, because it's probably… it's over here, sorry.
Benjamin Houghton: I want to make sure I,
Benjamin Houghton: Nope.
Benjamin Houghton: what am I talking about? Right?
Benjamin Houghton: What was I talking about? Well… I was talking about…
Benjamin Houghton: how, that's an overly simplistic drawing, right? So… Typically, like, you're gonna have…
Benjamin Houghton: Your… a typical transformer is gonna look something like this.
Benjamin Houghton: where E stands for encoder, and the output of 1 is going to go into the other, and you're gonna have, like, a series of encoders, right? And it's gonna be the same thing in the decoder. Remember, it's going to be something like this.
Benjamin Houghton: So these are… so the image… so the image goes in here, right, into the encoder. In here, you have the object queries that go into the decoder.
Benjamin Houghton: like this.
Benjamin Houghton: Decoder, decoder, decoder, and so… In each one of these little decoder blocks, you're gonna have both self.
Benjamin Houghton: and cross-attention. So, in self-attention, the queries attend to each other. In the cross-attention, the queries attend to the encoder outputs, right? Just like a traditional transformer framework. Just…
Benjamin Houghton: wanted to point that out. It's kind of interesting, I think, to me, that, like.
Benjamin Houghton: like, not only are the quick object queries gonna learn about, like, what's in the image, they're also gonna talk to each other and be like, oh, you're learning about that object? I guess I won't learn about that one. I don't… maybe that's… they're having some conversation, I don't… you know, like, it's kind of funny to think about, right?
Benjamin Houghton: So anyways, that's the way it works, sort of, I guess, right? From a high level, at least.
Benjamin Houghton: Any questions on that?
Benjamin Houghton: So far?
Benjamin Houghton: Alright.
Benjamin Houghton: Burger.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay.
Benjamin Houghton: Right, and so, yeah, and then you'll, you'll notice that after we get the decoder outputs, we'll, we'll feed them through a fully,
Benjamin Houghton: FFF, or F… I'm not sure what they fully…
Benjamin Houghton: FCN, or fully… what is… what is FFN? It's a fully connected layer, I'm just trying to remember… well, it's a weird abbreviation, not… don't remember what… why they call it FFN. Maybe I have it down here.
Benjamin Houghton: Thank you. Feed Forward Network, yeah. There's so many different names for them, right? Yeah, Feed Forward Network, right. Which is actually…
Benjamin Houghton: more… that is actually, like, the correct terminology. Like, nobody says multilayer perceptron anymore. Linear isn't, like.
Benjamin Houghton: and Professor James gets mad at me when I say that. It's not really a linear layer, because you… when you perform an activation, it's no longer linear. Like, if they were linear, you would just use linear regression. They're not… it's not linear, right?
Benjamin Houghton: So they're… they're not true linear layers. People say that because when you don't use, like, a linear activation… anyways.
Benjamin Houghton: That's neither here nor there,
Benjamin Houghton: But, fully… a feed-forward network is a… or a fully connected… they're both, I guess, correct, but that is the correct terminology. Right, so we do our fully connected layer, or our feed-forward layer, and we do our final prediction, and our final prediction is just going to be a simple vector that has the…
Benjamin Houghton: the, coordinates of the bounding boxes, the confidence, and the class. Like, what it is. So, whether it's a bird, or a dog, or whatever.
Benjamin Houghton: whatever it's been trained to do, where it is, where the box is, and how confident the model is. Because remember, this number is set. The number of object queries is not dynamic, right? It's a set number.
Benjamin Houghton: And so, some of them are not going to contain objects, right? So you need a way of, you know, encoding that, right?
Benjamin Houghton: So you can be flexible, whether you have a few things or a lot of things in your image.
Benjamin Houghton: All right, we can read through this real fast. There's just some more detail. I don't think it's really super important.
Benjamin Houghton: To read through this, but… We will,
Benjamin Houghton: I don't think this is, like, numbers you would ever… you don't need to memorize these for a quiz or anything. It's not something that you would memorize. It's more just to give, like, an understanding, like, kind of, like, visual… it's… I think it's helpful to have the numbers the first time you see it to, like, visualize the whole process, and can get a sense or a feeling for what's going on, though.
Benjamin Houghton: All right, so image size, 800x800 here. We have some CNN backbone. That's pretty big, too.
Benjamin Houghton: might want to double-check that number. It seems awfully big to me.
Benjamin Houghton: But whatever. I wrote it, so maybe it is correct, I don't know. Cnn backbone, so then we have a standard convolutional neural network, ResNet, 50-year 101. It doesn't have to be ResNet, could be any large convolutional neural network that you want to use to do feature extraction.
Benjamin Houghton: And then…
Benjamin Houghton: You'll get your feature maps, and then the feature maps is going to be, looks like C by H by W, right, where you have number of channels, number of height, number of rows, okay? So, then you'll flatten them.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? And turn it into a vector.
Benjamin Houghton: Right, so, you'll flatten it, and you'll get an H by W vector.
Benjamin Houghton: You'll add your 2D learnable parameters.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, I think in this version,
Benjamin Houghton: Each channel is going to attend to every other channel, right?
Benjamin Houghton: So, sequence length of HW, right.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay. So, basically, you're just going to take each channel and turn it into a one-dimensional vector. You'll add your learnable 2D positional encodings.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? So, remember, you have to have that to encode where stuff is in an image, so every single pixel knows where every other pixel is. This becomes the input sequence into the transformer encoder.
Benjamin Houghton: And then the transformer encoder, as we know, it does the self-attention, it learns the global relationships, it's composed of some number of multi-headed… multi-head self-attention layers, plus V4 networks.
Benjamin Houghton: The output is gonna be, a sequence of contextually rich tokens, still H by W tokens.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, so…
Benjamin Houghton: I apologize, and I, I just remember… I'm kind of remembering this now, but… or I said earlier that, remember in the vision transformer, we used patches?
Benjamin Houghton: this is the same thing, except instead of… the patch is just a single pixel now, right? So, you can have, you know, basically, each token is gonna be a pixel. So, you'll have a…
Benjamin Houghton: you'll have… it says right here, you'll have H by W tokens,
Benjamin Houghton: And so that would mean that, each… Kind of each token.
Benjamin Houghton: each token… a token is akin, or is basically, in this sense, instead of a token, we have a pixel, and then each pixel is going to be represented by some number of features, and initially they're represented by however many channels you have. So if you have, like, say, 2,048 channels, right? Right, so you would have, like.
Benjamin Houghton: Pixel, pixel, Pixel 1, and it would have 2,048 features, and then the next row down would be pixel 2, and it would be how many, so many features, so on and so forth, for however big the image is, or however big your feature map is.
Benjamin Houghton: times how many channels you have. So that's what the input would look like, right?
Benjamin Houghton: before it went into the encoder, right? So, the encoder doesn't self-attention, the output shape is the same as the input shape, is what this says. Again, don't need to memorize that for a quiz, right? Just wants you to think about different ways of doing it, and what, like, the way this particular, architecture, the DETR, the way they did it.
Benjamin Houghton: Transformer decoder, so we have the object queries, right? We talked about those.
Benjamin Houghton: We have a fixed number of them, and they are… they are learnable, like, they have learned positional embeddings, right? Each object query… each object query is a vector that the decoder learns to associate with potential objects, right? We do the… the cross attention in the decoder from the encoder's output.
Benjamin Houghton: Talked about that. And then the output produces n output embeddings, one for each query.
Benjamin Houghton: And these embeddings are then projected into some object predictions, projected meaning that it ran through a fully fee-forward layer.
Benjamin Houghton: So the decoder goes, right, the output goes through the classification head, and so they use a two, like, head… two prediction heads, or two head design. So they have the class prediction head that predicts the label, like, what type,
Benjamin Houghton: Including no object, so what it is, like a cat or a dog, or no object, right? So it would be a probability distribution over all object types, or over all classes, and a no object class.
Benjamin Houghton: And then we do our bounding box regression, right? So we have our center, our width, and our height.
Benjamin Houghton: And then finally, so we, yeah, we have our final output of N class predictions and n bounding boxes.
Benjamin Houghton: Huh?
Benjamin Houghton: this isn't necessarily a key innovation, it says key innovation here, it's just an important innovation, right? I wouldn't necessarily call it a key innovation, but the last thing we do is, like, Hungarian matching and loss, right? So, you might ask yourself, okay.
Benjamin Houghton: you know…
Benjamin Houghton: this is… you might not have thought about this yet, but why do we need to do this? Well.
Benjamin Houghton: this is just for training, step 5, right? So, once we've trained the model, or once we've got an output, right, let's say, we haven't… let's say we're trying to detect cats in our image, and here's our image, and here's our cat, okay?
Benjamin Houghton: Here's our cat. Alright.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? And
Benjamin Houghton: Let's say we have 3 queries, and one query is over here, and it, you know, it predicted, like, no class or something, and then we have a query over here.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? And it… it predicted cat. I don't know, it's a pretty bad prediction, right? And… but when we have, like, one more, right, like this, okay? And it also predicted cat.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, so, like, in this sense, like, yeah, well, it's obvious, like, this one's correct.
Benjamin Houghton: the yellow one, and the green one needs to be penalized, and the blue one's also correct. Well, but how do you know that, right? That's… you just arbitrarily decided that by looking at the image.
Benjamin Houghton: So we need a way to, kind of, to do this, like, in a…
Benjamin Houghton: structured manner. Because, like, I could erase this box.
Benjamin Houghton: And let's say the yellow box was actually, like, was actually, like, over here.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, it's closer, but, like, how do I know the green… how do I know the yellow box was completely wrong, and the green box was kind of also wrong? Like, how do I know which one for which object? So that's where Hungarian matching comes in. So what Hungarian matching does is it decides it's gonna minimize… it basically is going to match each box, each object.
Benjamin Houghton: And resulting in the lowest amount of cost, right? So, what does that mean? That means that we want to reduce the amount of error. So, the yellow box is the closest, so it's going to get trained on that object.
Benjamin Houghton: The green box doesn't… is going to get trained on, well, no, you predicted the wrong class. The regression doesn't matter for the green box, because there's no other cap.
Benjamin Houghton: You know? Now, let's say there was another cat, though.
Benjamin Houghton: Let me… let me draw another cat. Let's say there's another cat down here, okay? So, Hungarian Matching's gonna say, okay, green box, you're closest to this cat, yellow box, you're closest to this cat, you're gonna get assigned to those objects. And then we're going to perform our loss function, right? So, in this case.
Benjamin Houghton: you would… you would do both. You're gonna train
Benjamin Houghton: both the classification and the regression, because they're both cats, right? And you also got to correct, like, where the bounding boxes are. However, if, like, green… let's go back to that previous example, where the green box didn't have an object.
Benjamin Houghton: you're not going to penalize the regression head, right? So in this case, there's one cat, and the regression head, it's not its fault that it's not assigned to a cat. So you're not going to penalize its weights. You're only going to penalize the classification head, alright? So you're doing…
Benjamin Houghton: the classification and the regression at the same time, and you're just matching stuff based upon how close it is, and if it's, like, the correct class or not, right? Because it's not just… and I said… I made it very simple and said no clas… no class cat and cat, but it could be, like, remember, these are probability distributions. It's…
Benjamin Houghton: percentage cat, percentage dog, all these other things. So you use a cost formula to
Benjamin Houghton: figure out what the cost, the total cost is for… for… for every single scenario, every single possible scenario. You basically would do it, like, in a matrix. You can think of it as, like, a matrix, like, for every single object.
Benjamin Houghton: Every object and every single… every object of ground truth, because we have ground truth data, this is training, every single object and every single detection, we do a matrix, and we pair them all together.
Benjamin Houghton: say it's 10x10, so we pair them all, all 10 with all 10, and we figure out what is the cheapest way to do it, or the lowest cost. That's what Hungarian matching means, okay? Hungarian matching's been around since 1955, okay? It's nothing really to do with machine learning, per se. I guess maybe it is, I don't remember why.
Benjamin Houghton: they… what the original purpose was it. But that's what we do, for this. We do Hungarian matching, and that's how we assign different objects to different… different boxes, right? It's not… like, again, so now that you know what it is, like.
Benjamin Houghton: To say that it's, like, a key innovation is a little bit of a misnomer, right? It's just how you train
Benjamin Houghton: In this instance. Does that make sense, though?
Benjamin Houghton: We're gonna talk about Hungarian matching
Benjamin Houghton: more when we talk about, object tracking, too. Because we'll use it… we have to use object tracking, because we're in the same scenario in object tracking, where we have, detections, and we, basically we have objects moving, you know, across…
Benjamin Houghton: various frames, and we have to assign, like, detections to what we call tracks, okay? Because we have, like, an object moving through a frame, and we have, in each frame, a detection, we have to assign detections to tracks. So anyways.
Benjamin Houghton: So we'll use the same concept of Hungarian matching, again, just not quite the same way we did here, all right? And so what… the cost is based upon class prediction and box similarity, or intersection over union. I think… oh yeah, I do have a,
Benjamin Houghton: a matching… a cost matching function down here if you want to see, like, the full equation. Again, you don't need to know that, right? You just need to know that it's gonna balance, it's gonna… the Hungarian matching is gonna balance the prediction and, the similarity in the class prediction, all right?
Benjamin Houghton: The loss function, cross entropy, because we're doing… we're doing multi-class classification, bounding box, it's going to be some type of regression loss, so here you have L1, right, plus, GIO, or intersection of reunion, generalized intersection of reunion, okay?
Benjamin Houghton: Alright.
Benjamin Houghton: I'm gonna kind of skip through some of this stuff. This is just a summary, we already talked about this. Advantages and limitations, let's just take a glance at this. No anchors, no expression, we already talked about a lot of that. Limitations, slow convergence, needs a lot of data, struggles with… the early versions struggle with small.
Benjamin Houghton: straw, early versions.
Benjamin Houghton: here's more detail about Hungarian matching. I'm not gonna… I don't think this is, like, super important, like, I just kind of, like, drew you a whole diagram that this is kind of saying what I said in, on the slide here, but it solves the assignment problem, right? It matches the ground truths.
Benjamin Houghton: and the predictions to minimize some total cost. Matches are chosen greedily for best alignment, meaning where the lowest cost, it's not a learned parameter, right? And we're doing this during training when we have ground truth data and we have predictions.
Benjamin Houghton: And here's the cost function, right? Again, so you can see the class mismatch, the bounding box locations, right? So,
Benjamin Houghton: Right, so here's… here's the cost function that… what makes a good match.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, that's it. So, any questions?
Benjamin Houghton: I will say,
Benjamin Houghton: Hopefully, now that you've kind of seen this, like, a lot of you now have seen, like.
Benjamin Houghton: Transformers with language.
Benjamin Houghton: you've seen, with images, you've seen it maybe with time series data, and you're kind of, like, starting to understand and realize that, like, we're just doing the same thing over and over, just doing it differently. Like, we're just using… we're just taking our data, and we're just reshaping it to get it into the right format, so we can put it through some transformer, do the attention mechanism, and that's the way multimodal AI works, right?
Benjamin Houghton: Hopefully you're kind of… pick up on that, and I have some intuition for that now.
Benjamin Houghton: Is there any questions on today's topics?
Benjamin Houghton: And I owe you guys a study guide for this lecture, too.
Benjamin Houghton: All right, so we'll go ahead and… Michael, I think you're doing… are you doing the presentation? I think you are, right? Okay, great. You can come get set up whenever… whenever you're ready.
Benjamin Houghton: I'll move my stuff out of the way.
Benjamin Houghton: Let's see, too, if that one doesn't work.